The reason for examining the pupils in primary eye care is to see if there's any obvious visible
evidence of disease, such as cataract or trauma, and to see if the pupil constricts to bright light.
This tells us if the optic nerve or retina at the back of the eye are healthy.
Start by explaining what you're going to do and check the patient is happy.
Then look at the eyes to see if the pupils are black, round and
equal, and if there are any other signs such as squint or droopy,
eyelid.
Then the lights in the room then check the direct pupil response with a bright light
by looking for a brisk and obvious constriction.
If this is present then the optic nerve and retina
at the back of the eye are likely to be healthy.
If the pupil fails to constrict then there is likely
to be disease of the optic nerve such as glaucoma or the retina such
as detachment or blockage of
blood supply.
It can be hard to see the black pupil against the dark brown iris and so you'll
have to get in close.
When healthy the pupil should constrict briskly and obviously to bright
light in a dim room.
Even in this eye with a grey white pupil due to cataract the pupil
should still constrict despite the cataract as long as the optic nerve and retina at the
the back of the eye are healthy.
If the pupil only constricts a little and slowly then there
is likely to be disease at the back of the eye and the visual
outcome from cataract surgery
may be poor.
When the pupil response is entirely absent, the chance of visual improvement after
cataract surgery is very low.
Remember, when examining the pupil, first look to confirm
It is black, round and equal and then in the dim room reacts briskly
and obviously to a bright light.